<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Prajwal Bharadwaj</title>
    <link>//localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Prajwal Bharadwaj</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="//localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>VG&amp;M Harry Potter Event 2024</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/scicom/2024oct26-vgm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/scicom/2024oct26-vgm/</guid>
      <description>Harry Potter themed outreach event at the Victoria Gallery &amp;amp; Museum, Liverpool</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DiMeN Science Communication Competition</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/scicom/2024jul17-dimenytshort/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/scicom/2024jul17-dimenytshort/</guid>
      <description>My entry was submitted to the Max Perutz Award organised by the MRC, UKRI</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pint of Science Talk 2024</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/scicom/2024may14-pintofscience/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/scicom/2024may14-pintofscience/</guid>
      <description>I spoke about plasmids at the Pint of Science event at Ship &amp;amp; Mitre, Liverpool</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>British Science Week Event 2024</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/scicom/2024mar16-bsw/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/scicom/2024mar16-bsw/</guid>
      <description>Microbiology outreach event for the British Science Week event the Victoria Gallery &amp;amp; Museum, Liverpool</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Genetic Mischeif Makers: The Thrilling Tale of Jumping Genes</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/blog/2023-12-02-shotsofscience1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Dec 2023 12:32:45 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/blog/2023-12-02-shotsofscience1/</guid>
      <description>Jumping genes are powerful hitchhikers that inhabit DNA of all walks of life from microbes to humans. These rogue elements have the remarkable ability to rewire bacterial genomes providing boosts and superpowers to their hosts. Join me on this journey to unravel the secrets of these miniature genetic adventurers showcasing their quest for survival and self-interest within the world of bacteria. They are short snippets of DNA but they can do so much! It&amp;rsquo;s a story of intrigue, innovation, and evolution that&amp;rsquo;s sure to leave you astounded by the tiny but mighty inhabitants of the bacterial world.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shots of Science Talk 2023</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/scicom/2023nov17-shotsofscience/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/scicom/2023nov17-shotsofscience/</guid>
      <description>Speaking about mobile genetics elements at the Tempest on Tithebarn St., Liverpool</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VG&amp;M Harry Potter Event 2023</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/scicom/2023oct28-vgm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/scicom/2023oct28-vgm/</guid>
      <description>Harry Potter themed outreach event at the Victoria Gallery &amp;amp; Museum, Liverpool</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IISc Open Day Event</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/scicom/2023mar04-iiscopenday/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/scicom/2023mar04-iiscopenday/</guid>
      <description>Open Day Event Discussing How Complexity Arises by Simple Adaptations at IISc, Bangalore</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-backstory&#34;&gt;My Backstory&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Brought up in cheerful and welcoming South Bengaluru, I grew up loving to play cricket, exploring the imaginative islands that spanned my home and reading books untill I ran out of them.&#xA;I spent all of my 13 years of Education at my second home, the Kumaran Group of Institutions. For the most part, Kumarans really shaped much of what I am today. Joining IISER to study Science, really, in many ways, began the next chapter of my life.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/science/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;plasmid-host-interactions-in-pseudomonas-aeruginosa&#34;&gt;Plasmid Host Interactions in &lt;em&gt;Pseudomonas aeruginosa&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;antimicrobial-resistance-is-a-big-treat&#34;&gt;Antimicrobial resistance is a big treat&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The growing threat of Antimicrobial Resistance (AMR) is predicted to cause the death of 10 million people annually by 2050. The remarkable ability of bacteria to rapidly acquire resistance to antibiotics is a major challenge for healthcare professionals and the pharmaceutical industry.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Even when it is possible to treat infections caused by multi-drug resistant pathogens, it can be difficult and expensive, and there is a dearth of new antimicrobials coming to market owing to rapid emergence of resistance in the face of prolonged development and testing. Preventing the emergence of AMR in potential pathogens is therefore an important goal for evolutionary microbiology.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Work Experience</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/cv/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/cv/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;phd-with-dr-james-hall&#34;&gt;PhD with Dr. James Hall&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Plasmid-Host Dynamics in the context of Antibiotic Resistance&lt;/strong&gt;&#xA;&lt;em&gt;October 2023 - ongoing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul class=&#39;container&#39;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt; Studying persistence of antimicrobial resistance as a function of plasmid persistence in the host &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt; Understanding the interaction dynamics of the plasmid and the host genome &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;research-project-with-dr-samay-pande&#34;&gt;Research Project with Dr. Samay Pande&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Research Project on evolution of antibiotic resistance&lt;/strong&gt;&#xA;&lt;em&gt;August 2022 - June 2023&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul class=&#39;container&#39; style=&#39;display list-item;&#39;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt; Understanding the influence of multiple selection-constrains on the de-novo evolution of antibiotic resistance&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt; Studying evolution of antibiotic resistance in prey bacteria in the presence of a predator and evolution of escape strategies by the prey. The model system used was of M xanthus (predator) and E coli, P fluorescence and S enterica (prey).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt; Experimental coevolution of M xanthus and three prey bacteria - Microbial culture techniques&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt; Analysis of predatory efficiency of and competition between clones of M xanthus from a population mixing evolution experiment&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt; Standardisation of NGS based Frequency Analysis of M xanthus and E coli clones&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;masters-thesis-with-dr-frederic-bertels&#34;&gt;Masters Thesis with Dr. Frederic Bertels&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Studying the dynamics of REPIN movement in bacterial genomes&lt;/strong&gt;&#xA;&lt;em&gt;March 2021 - June 2022&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
